Finding Aid for the Reverend James M. Lawson, Jr. Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
- Organizations – Fellowship of Reconciliation (FOR) – Box 37
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Newsletter – “Current Issues” – 1962
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Newsletter – “Current Issues” – n.d.
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Newsletter – “Disarmament News” _ 1960
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Newsletter – “Facts for Action” – 1995-1998
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Newsletter – “FORWORD” – 1975
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Newsletter – “The Mustard Seed” - 1961
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Executive Committee Minutes – 1960-1961
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Executive Committee Meeting – 1998
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Magazine – “Fellowship” – 1948
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Magazine – “Fellowship” – 1959
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Magazine – “Fellowship” – 1960
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Magazine – “Fellowship” – 1961
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Magazine – “Fellowship – 1964
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Magazine - “Fellowship” – 1976
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Magazine – “Fellowship” – 1980
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Magazine – “Fellowship” – 1996
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Magazine – “Fellowship” – 1998
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Magazine – “Fellowship” – 1999
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Magazine Reprint – “Motive” - 1960
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Catalog- Cards, Calendars, Gifts – 1998-1999
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – News Release – 1995
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – News Release – 1998
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Finance Committee Meeting – 1999
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Finance Committee Members – 1996
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Financial Statements – 1997 and 1998
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Pamphlet - “How to Practice Nonviolence” – 1958
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Poster – Iraq – 1996
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Issues for Discussion – 1995
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Brochure – “Jesus and the Way to Peace” – n.d.
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Los Angeles/SCLC – Article – 1983
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Poster – Martin Luther King, Jr. – n.d.
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Members of FOR Attending Colleges – 1957-1958
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Members of Nashville FOR – n.d.
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Membership List – n.d.
- Organizations – Fellowship of Reconciliation (FOR) – Box 38
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Catalogue – United Nations Films - 1957
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Magazine – “Reconciliation International” – December 1998
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Newsletter “Panama Update” – 1996
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Newsletter – “Regional News Notes” – 1959
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Newspaper Clippings – Weapons and Arms Control – 1994
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – National Conference – August 1996
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – National Council Meeting – May 1996
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – National Council Meeting – May 1998
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – National Council Meeting – October 1998
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Nature of Work of F.O.R. – n.d.
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Occasional Papers - 1959
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Occasional Papers – 1960
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Occasional Papers – 1961
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Occasional Papers – Peacemaker Research Commission – n.d.
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Occasional Papers – n.d.
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Outline – Pacifism – n.d.
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Pamphlet – War Without Violence – 1959
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Personnel Policies – 1995-1997
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Packet – Campaign to Save a Generation – 1999
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Packet – Stop the War in Kosova – 1999
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Planned Giving Policies – 1999
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Poster – Segregation by Statute – 1949
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Program Work – August 1998
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Remarks – Senate Foreign Relation Subcommittee on UN Affairs – Senator John F. Kennedy, Chairman – July 1957
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Report on the Year’s Work – 1958-1959
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Report on Vietnam – 1965
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Report – Visit to Saigon – 1967
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Reprints – “The Progressive” – 1960
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Resource Center for Nonviolence – 1996
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Summer Campaign – “A New Millennium of Nonviolence – 1999
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Workshops – Nonviolence – 1958
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Workshops – Nonviolence – 1960
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Workshops – Nonviolence – 1961
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – Workshops – Nonviolence - Notes on the Little Rock Nine – Dunbar Ogden – n.d.
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation – World Peace Broadcasting Foundation – 1960
- Organizations – Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC) – Box 39
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Constitution and By-Laws – n.d.
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Incoming – 1959
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Incoming – 1960
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Incoming – 1961
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Incoming – 1962
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Incoming – 1963
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Incoming – 1965
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Incoming – 1968
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Incoming – 1978
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Incoming – 1984
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Incoming – 1988
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Incoming – n.d.
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Outgoing – 1959
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Outgoing – 1960
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Outgoing – 1962
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Outgoing – 1963
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Outgoing - 1964
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Correspondence – Outgoing – 1967
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – American Foundation on Non-Violence – Correspondence – Outgoing – 1967
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – C.O.F.O Mississippi Freedom School Curriculum – 1964
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Convention – 7th Annual – n.d.
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Convention – 20th Anniversary – 1977
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Sermon – 25th Anniversary of Founding of SCLC – 1982
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Convention 27th Annual – August 1984
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Convention - Keynote Address – by James M. Lawson – August 1961
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Annual Meeting – September 1961
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – California Project – 1982
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Congressional Black Caucus – 1974
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Center for Non-Violence – 1993-1994
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Fall Session – September 1959
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – First Annual Martin Luther King Memorial Lecture – April 1975
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Funeral – Alfred Daniel Williams King, Sr. – July 1969
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – General Program – 1960-1961
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Leadership Training Program and Citizenship Schools – n.d.
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Martin Luther King Birthday Celebration – January 1987
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Newsletter – “The Crusader” – November 1959
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Newsletter – “The Legacy” – March/April 1984
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Newspaper Clippings – Freedom Schools – 1964
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Newspaper Clippings – 1960
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Newspaper Clippings – 1971
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Newspaper Clippings – 1985
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Newspaper Clippings – n.d.
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Southern Christian Minister’s Conference of Mississippi – An Institute on Nonviolent Resistance to Segregation - September 1959
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Statement – Joseph E. Lowery – June 1986
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Workshop – Jackson, Mississippi – 1964
- Organizations – Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC) – Box 40
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Brochure – “This is SCLC” – n.d.
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Delegates to Youth Leadership Conference – April 1960
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Journal - “Soul Force” – 1968
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Magazine – “SCLC West” – May-June 1977
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Martin Luther King Memorial Center – includes letter from Coretta Scott King – 1971
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Meeting of Black Churchmen with Ralph Abernathy – February 1972
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Minutes – Tennessee Christian Leadership Conference – September 1960
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – National Convention – August 1980
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference - Newsletter - Convention Issue – 1961
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Nonviolent Workshop – May 1961
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Nonviolent Workshop – Notes, Sermons, Meetings – n.d.
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Position Paper – “The Time is Now for Progressive Leadership” – 1999
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Press Release – “Nonviolent Attitude Shows Strength – Not Weakness” – July 1959
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference - Prince Edward School Closure – n.d.
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – National Board of Directors Luncheon – August 1979
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Program on Education in the Philosophy and Program of Nonviolence – n.d.
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Proposal – Martin Luther King Speaks – 1969
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Publications – n.d.
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Report on Special Projects – 1962-1963
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Report on Workshops – March 1962
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Resolutions – 1981
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – SCLC/LA – Nation of Islam – 1985
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Southwide Voter Registration Prospectus – n.d.
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Statement to the South and Nation – January 1957
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Suggested Program for Workshop on Christian Nonviolence – n.d.
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Writings – Martin Luther King – 1956-1962
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference – Youth March for Integrated Schools - 1958
- Book Draft – Box 45
  - Correspondence – Incoming – 1960
  - Correspondence – Outgoing – 1960
  - Correspondence – Incoming – 1961
  - Correspondence – Outgoing – 1961
  - Correspondence – Incoming – 1962
  - Correspondence – Incoming – 1963
  - Newspaper Clippings – Freedom Riders – 1961
  - Newspaper Clippings – Prayer in Schools – 1962
  - Nonviolence Series for Newsletter – 1960
  - Notes from Harvie Branscomb – n.d.
  - Press Release – [1962]
  - Report on Nashville – 1960
  - Sermon – “What is the Issue” – 1960
  - Statement to the Press – By Martin Luther King – April 1960
  - Students v. Segregation – March 1960
  - Talk for the Mississippi Movement – September 1959
  - Writings – “The Call of the Prayer Vigil” – n.d.
  - Writings – “From a Lunch Counter Stool” – n.d.
  - Writings – “Violence and Nonviolence” – n.d.
  - Working Outline – n.d.
  - Chapter I
  - Chapter II
  - Chapter III
  - Chapter IV
  - Chapter V
  - Chapter VI
  - Chapter VII
  - Chapter VIII
- Return to Vanderbilt University, 2006-2010
  - Correspondence – Incoming – 2006
  - Correspondence – Incoming – 2007
  - Correspondence – Incoming – 2008
  - Correspondence – Incoming – 2009
  - Correspondence – Incoming - 2010
  - Correspondence – Itineraries – 2006
  - Correspondence – Outgoing – 2006
  - Correspondence – Outgoing – 2007
  - Course – ‘The Nonviolent Struggle” – 2006
  - Course – “The Nonviolent Struggle” – 2007
  - Course – “The Nonviolent Struggle” – 2008
  - Engagements – 2006
  - Engagements – 2007
  - Engagements – 2008
  - Engagements – 2009
  - Engagements – 2010
  - 9/11 Incident Event – 2006
  - Interview Tapes (3) – ca.2008
  - Living Wage Panel – 2006
  - Living Wage Panel – Photograph Contact Sheets – ca. 2006
  - Magazine Article – “Bless You, Mrs. Degrafinried” – n.d.
  - Newspaper Clippings – 2006
  - Newspaper Clippings – 2007
  - Newspaper Clippings – 2008
  - Poster – Martin Luther King, Jr. Commemoration – 2007
  - Poster – We Speak For Ourselves – 2008
  - Press Release – 2006
  - Program – Inauguration of the James M. Lawson, Jr. Chair – 2007
  - Program – Martin Luther King, Jr. – 2010
  - Publication – Labor – “40 Years Since King: The Legacy” – Spring 2008
  - Calendar – 2006-2007
  - Calendar - 2008-2009
  - Calendar- Community Events and Continuing Education – Fall 2009